[{"question": "Kann ich im 3. Semester des MiM Programms max. 1 Advanced Seminar und 2 Limited Courses belegen, also max 18 ECTS?", "answer": "Grundsätzlich ist Ihr Studienprogramm so strukturiert, dass Sie idealerweise jedes Semester 30 Credits erfüllen. Advanced Seminars und Other Limited Courses sind keine Pflicht, aber empfehlenswert zu belegen. Die Anzahl der Advanced Seminars bzw. Other Limited Courses, die Sie belegen können, hängt davon ab, wo Sie einen Fixplatz erhalten. Es gibt keine Vorgaben bei der Wahl Ihrer Electives, sodass Sie jegliche Module wählen können, die unter den wirtschaftswissenschaftlichen Wahlmodulen bzw. den sonstigen wirtschaftswissenschaftlichen Wahlmodulen in Ihrem Studienbaum in TUMonline aufgeführt sind.", "topic": "AW  Frage zu MiM 3  Semester  Wahlfächer", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Can I proceed with the master thesis registration and the thesis itself under the supervision of Mr. [REDACTED] and Prof. [REDACTED] from the Professorship of Real Estate Development, which falls outside the school of management?", "answer": "You need to fill in and send back the attached application form. Once you return the form, we will review your request for supervision from another TUM school and get back to you.", "topic": "AW  Requesting permission for master thesis", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Ist es notwendig, dass ich mich für die Anerkennung des Kurses bei der Hochschule für Philosophie immatrikuliere? Oder reicht es, wenn [REDACTED] schriftlich bestätigt, dass ich an den Vorlesungen und der Klausur am Ende teilgenommen habe? Zudem hatte mich [REDACTED] gebeten herauszufinden wie die Prüfungsleistung ausschauen muss, damit die TUM diese akzeptiert? Ist eine schriftliche Klausur Voraussetzung, oder wäre auch eine mündliche Klausur akzeptabel?", "answer": "Eine Anmeldung müsste daher über TUMonline problemlos möglich sein und Sie müssten auch nach Ablegen des Moduls keinen Antrag auf Anerkennung stellen. Die Prüfungsmodalitäten für dieses Modul sind ebenfalls festgelegt und Sie können diese beim Klicken auf das Buchsymbol in TUMonline auch einsehen.", "topic": "AW  Externes Wahlmodul  Philosophie der KI  (Matrikelnummer  [REDACTED])", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Kann ich mich für Veranstaltungen anmelden und zu diesen erscheinen, auch wenn ich bis zum Semesterstart noch nicht vollständig an der TUM School of Management immatrikuliert bin und das Abschlusszeugnis meines Bachelors noch nachreichen muss? Was passiert im Falle einer verzögerten Immatrikulation hinsichtlich der Modulanmeldung und Teilnahme an Veranstaltungen?", "answer": "Ja, Sie können und sollten zu den Lehrveranstaltungen erscheinen, auch wenn Sie zu Vorlesungsbeginn noch nicht vollständig immatrikuliert sind. Es empfiehlt sich, die gewünschten Lehrveranstaltungen zu besuchen und sich nachträglich über TUMonline anzumelden, sobald die vollständige Immatrikulation erfolgt ist. Dies gilt besonders für Pflichtmodule, die in den ersten zwei Semestern belegt werden sollten, und für die auch Übungen und Tutorien angeboten werden, für die eine Anmeldung ebenfalls über TUMonline möglich ist. Die Immatrikulation setzt die Einreichung aller erforderlichen Dokumente voraus, einschließlich des BA-Abschlusszeugnisses, das nachgereicht werden kann, sofern dies im Zeitrahmen des ersten Semesters erfolgt.", "topic": "AW  Modulanmeldung MiM ohne BA Abschlusszeugnis", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Kann ich die oben genannten Module aus meinem Bachelorstudium für bestimmte Pflichtmodule meines Masterstudiengangs anerkennen lassen und insbesondere die zwei Module für das eine Modul \"[REDACTED]\" im Master?", "answer": "Ja, eine Anerkennung vorab abgelegter Module ist möglich, wenn keine wesentlichen Unterschiede hinsichtlich der Lernergebnisse bestehen. Die Entscheidung darüber trifft der jeweilige Modulverantwortliche des MiM-Studiengangs. Es ist auch möglich, sich zwei Module für ein Modul anerkennen zu lassen, wenn die inhaltliche Passung und Lernziele äquivalent sind. Eine Vorabprüfung wird nicht durchgeführt, und man muss sich zunächst entscheiden, ob man den Anerkennungsprozess beginnen möchte. Informationen und das entsprechende Formular befinden sich im Downloadcenter.", "topic": "AW  Modulanerkennungen", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Can you assist with the issue of being rejected from all seminar courses due to incorrect preferences?", "answer": "Unfortunately, if you have chosen the incorrect preferences, you are excluded from the seminar’s allocation procedure. However, you could attend the kick-off event of the seminars you are interested in, as there might be open spots due to no-shows of other students who had been allocated a place.", "topic": "AW  Rejection from all seminar courses due to incorrect preferences", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Given my previous academic achievements and the B1 certificate, am I sufficient to fulfill the German language requirements for my new degree program?", "answer": "For the Master in Management, you have to provide proof of proficiency in German at level A 1.1 at the end of your second semester at the latest. With your prior courses and certificates in German, you fulfill this requirement.", "topic": "AW  Inquiry Regarding German Language Requirements for My Changed Degree ([REDACTED])", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Ist es notwendig, dass ich mich für die Anerkennung des Kurses bei der Hochschule für Philosophie immatrikuliere? Oder reicht es, wenn [REDACTED] schriftlich bestätigt, dass ich an den Vorlesungen und der Klausur am Ende teilgenommen habe? Wie muss die Prüfungsleistung aussehen, damit die TUM diese akzeptiert? Ist eine schriftliche Klausur Voraussetzung, oder wäre auch eine mündliche Klausur akzeptabel?", "answer": "Eine Anmeldung müsste über TUMonline problemlos möglich sein und Sie müssten auch nach Ablegen des Moduls keinen Antrag auf Anerkennung stellen. Die Prüfungsmodalitäten für dieses Modul sind ebenfalls festgelegt und Sie können diese beim Klicken auf das Buchsymbol in TUMonline auch einsehen.", "topic": "AW  Externes Wahlmodul  Philosophie der KI  (Matrikelnummer)", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Ist das „soll“ in der FSPO §46 (3), welches aussagt, dass die Masterarbeit in Englisch verfasst werden soll, also eigentlich ein „muss“ oder ist das nur ein Wunsch?", "answer": "Das „soll“ ist tatsächlich kein „muss“. Auch in der Modulbeschreibung des Moduls „Master Thesis“ in TUMonline ist die Sprache mit Deutsch/Englisch angegeben, und es kommt vor, dass Studierende ihre Arbeit in Deutsch schreiben, wenn es zum Thema passt. Die Abfassung Ihrer Masterarbeit auf Deutsch steht also aus administrativer und rechtlicher Perspektive nichts im Wege.", "topic": "AW  Masterarbeit anmelden", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "If I start writing my thesis in July, can I still register for subjects in the next WS[REDACTED]? Or do I have to complete all my credits this SS[REDACTED]? More generally, is it possible to have pending credits after submitting the master's thesis?", "answer": "Your thesis should be your last exam, but this is not mandatory. You can still take modules after submission of your thesis. This also means that you do not have to complete all required credits this summer semester.", "topic": "AW  Question about master thesis registration", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Can the \"Principles of Economics\" course I took during my bachelor's degree be recognized and credited towards my current program, allowing me to choose a different module?", "answer": "For recognition and credit transfer, there should not be any essential differences between the modules, especially concerning learning outcomes. The equivalence is examined by the person in charge of the relevant module on the MiM program. You need to consult the information and fill out the form available in the download center for a credit transfer. Recognition is only possible after enrollment in the new program and within the first year of study.", "topic": "AW  About “Principles of Economics” Course", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "What does the FRV column signify in the TUM online page under a student's file?", "answer": "FRV stands for \"Fristverlängerung\" which means deadline extension. It indicates the number of Covid-related study extensions granted to the student, to accommodate any problems arising from the Covid-19 pandemic. For the student who inquired, the number 3 in the FRV column means they were granted 3 extra semesters to meet the academic progress requirements.", "topic": "AW  FRV column in TUM online page", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "What should I do since the marketing chair does not accept external topics, and I am interested in a topic under Marketing?", "answer": "In fact, it is up to the chairs to decide whether they supervise only assigned topics or accept proposals from students. However, to my knowledge, the majority of the chairs from TUM School of Management, do accept proposals from students; this does not apply to the marketing chair, you are right.", "topic": "AW  Thesis supervision", "program": "Master in Management in Munich"}, {"question": "Can you send me a credit transfer form and should I send it back to you when I'm done, or to someone else?", "answer": "You can find an instruction on how to get credits recognized and all the necessary forms in our download section <https://www.mgt.tum.de/download-center>.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Where is the link or where are the Project Studies published, how does the application process work, and are there boundaries on how many hours a week students can work and what is expected from the company?", "answer": "There is a Moodle course you can join for information about the project studies: [REDACTED] In this Moodle course, you can find all information about the project studies.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I combine my Project Work with my mandatory international experience by doing it abroad?", "answer": "Unfortunately, you can’t combine the international experience with the project work, because the project work is done in Munich and you have to write there a scientific article.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I use the Spanish course for the module of communication skills, and get it accredited for credits and the grade? Moreover, which steps do I need to take to accredit this course and can I choose if I want to accredit it, in case my grade is below my general expectations for my GPA?", "answer": "Yes, you can use the Spanish course for the module of communication skills, as long as the course has at least 3 ECTS. To accredit the course at [REDACTED], email the grade management once the grading appears on your transcript, and they can allocate it as Communication Skills. Communication Skills is graded as pass or fail, so your grade will not impact your grades.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I take the retake exam in Munich and have the results recognized in Heilbronn? What is the procedure for taking retake exams during a leave of absence? Is it mandatory to have successfully completed all specialization courses before engaging in project work?", "answer": "Yes, you can take the retake in Munich, but the content might differ from Heilbronn. For the retake exams during the leave of absence, the procedure is the same as without leave of absence; register for the retake exams in TUMonline. It is recommended but not mandatory to complete all specialization courses before project work; you should have completed the courses related to your project work specialization.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Will the elective courses I registered for still take place even if the number of participants is low, or will they be cancelled, and should I register for others if needed?", "answer": "The responsible professor for the elective course may decide to cancel the module if not enough people register. If that happens after the registration deadline, you can email us with the module ID of another course you'd like to take, and we will register you manually if there are spots available.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "So in this case, shall I present the first slide or the contents from textbooks of each course? And I attach the translation behind?", "answer": "Unfortunately, we definitely need confirmation about the course content from your previous university. This can be a module handbook or a certificate about the course content.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "What documents are required for transferring disciplines, when and where should they be taken, and what steps are expected to be taken for a Bachelor's degree in Management and Technology at TUM Campus Heilbronn?", "answer": "You can find an instruction on how to get credits recognized in our download section at <https://www.mgt.tum.de/download-center>. All necessary forms are also available there.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Kann ich als Studentin alle meine Prüfungen in München ablegen, auch wenn einige Prüfungen ursprünglich in einer anderen Stadt vorgesehen sind?", "answer": "Die Teilnahme an den Prüfungen in München ist leider nicht in jedem Fall ganz ohne Probleme möglich. Während die International Experience Prüfung in München geschrieben werden kann, müssen die Module, die sich inhaltlich unterscheiden, noch einmal von dem jeweiligen Professor in [REDACTED] anerkannt werden.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I appear for the 'Economics 1: Microeconomics' exam in Campus Straubing as a [REDACTED] student, is the exam in English, will the credits be transferable to my course, and if I don't pass can I still take the exam in Heilbronn on [REDACTED]?", "answer": "It is planned for [REDACTED] students to take the exams of the mandatory management modules in Heilbronn, but you can take exams in Munich and Straubing if they are equivalent to the modules in Heilbronn. However, the equivalency will not be checked in advance, so you need to ensure that the module contents match and apply for credit recognition via email if the modules don’t show up afterward.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Is the math exam in [REDACTED] valid in terms of credits, is it the same as ours in content, and would you recommend me taking it?", "answer": "The retake exam of Mathematics in [REDACTED] will take place during the regular exam period in the summer semester. It is your decision whether to attempt the exam in [REDACTED]. If you do, you need to register for it during the registration period. Be aware that the content may be slightly different due to a different professor teaching the module. If you pass the exam in [REDACTED], you must apply for credit recognition afterwards, as the module is not listed in your curriculum.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Ist es möglich, ein Fach von meinem Auslandssemester anerkennen zu lassen, welches ich schon an der TUM bestanden habe; und wenn ja, würde das meine Note ersetzen (wenn ich das wollte)?", "answer": "Leider ist die Anerkennung von bereits erfolgreich bestandenen Modulen nicht möglich, d.h. eine Notenverbesserung ist an der TUM nicht möglich. Sie können sich die Veranstaltungen jedoch als Zusatzleistungen auf das TUM Zeugnis aufnehmen lassen.", "topic": "Emails PM", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can you please help me unselect this management specialisation and pick Management and Marketing as specialisation?", "answer": "I have forwarded your email to my colleagues from the Grade Management Office. They are responsible for all grade and examination-related questions and will reply to your email shortly. However, due to the number of inquiries, answering your email may take a few days.", "topic": "AW Urgent help for choice of management specialisation in Course Consumer Science", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Is it possible to enroll in the study place without the final document?", "answer": "You can find all relevant information on enrollment, including admission offers, application documents, acceptance of study places, and semester fees, here: [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW Question regarding enrollment", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Does having a Bachelor's in Mechanical Engineering and experience as a Technical Team Manager for a Formula Student team qualify me for pursuing an M.Sc in Management and Technology? Is there an alternative course that I might have missed?", "answer": "Please get in touch with our colleagues from our Admission Office; they are responsible for answering questions from applicants and prospective students.", "topic": "Re", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Who should I talk to about validating subjects I'm choosing for an Erasmus at TUM?", "answer": "I have forwarded your email to my colleagues from the International Office; they are responsible for questions on recognition of courses from abroad and will reply to your email shortly.", "topic": "AW Validation of credits to Erasmus", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Kann ich die erforderlichen ECTS für den Zugang zum MMT-Programm an der TUM nachholen, indem ich Bachelorkurse oder andere Kurse an der TUM belege?", "answer": "Bitte kontaktieren Sie unser Admission Office über: [REDACTED] für Fragen von Bewerber*innen und Studieninteressierten. Wenn Ihnen bereits ein Studienplatz an der TUM angeboten wurde und Sie Fragen zur Annahme Ihres Zulassungsangebots und Ihrer Einschreibung haben, wenden Sie sich bitte an das TUM Center for Study and Teaching: [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW TUM MMT ECTS KRITERIEN", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Kindly advise if the documents are not notarized correctly as per the standards and need to be notarized again by the University or the German Embassy to complete the enrollment process.", "answer": "To resolve your issue, please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching at [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW Enrollment Process  - Muhammad Asim Saleem - TUM ID", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Kindly advise if the documents are not notarized correctly as per the standards and need to be notarized again by the University or the German Embassy to complete the enrollment process.", "answer": "To resolve your issue, please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching at [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW Enrollment Process  - Muhammad Asim Saleem - TUM ID go69sih", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Ist GMAT für den Management- und Technologie-Masterstudiengang erforderlich?", "answer": "Unsere Kolleg*innen unseres Admission Office sind für die Beantwortung von Fragen von Bewerber*innen und Studieninteressierten verantwortlich. Bitte kontaktieren Sie meine Kolleg*innen über: [REDACTED].", "topic": "AW Über den Masterstudiengang Management und Technologie", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Wer ist für die Anrechnung von Studienleistungen aus dem Ausland zuständig, und an wen soll ich mich wenden, damit die Kurse, die ich im Auslandssemester belege, für eine mögliche Anrechnung geprüft werden?", "answer": "Ich habe Ihre E-Mail an meine Kolleg*innen unseres International Office weitergeleitet. Sie sind für alle Fragen über Anrechnung von Studienleistungen aus dem Ausland zuständig.", "topic": "AW Anerkennung von Leistungen aus dem Ausland ", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "If I take a leave of absence, would I still keep my enrollment? It is a requirement for the internship.", "answer": "To resolve your issue, please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching at studium@tum.de", "topic": "AW Internship", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Can you tell me whom to contact to solve the problem of potentially being exmatriculated due to not paying the student union fee on time?", "answer": "Please contact the Semester Fees Management concerning this matter ([REDACTED])", "topic": "AW Renewal of Registration", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Wie kann die Gültigsetzung meiner letzten Klausurnote beschleunigt werden und wie lange dauert es nach gültiger Übernahme der letzten Klausur, bis ich mein Zeugnis erhalte bzw. wie kann ich ein vorläufiges Zeugnis zur Immatrikulation beantragen?", "answer": "Für alle Fragen zur Immatrikulation sind die Kolleg*innen des TUM Center for Study & Teaching die richtigen Ansprechpartner. Außerdem finden Sie sämtliche relevanten Informationen zu den Abschlussdokumenten unter dem angegebenen Link. Ein vorläufiges Zeugnis kann möglicherweise dort oder durch direkte Anfrage beim TUM Center for Study & Teaching beantragt werden.", "topic": "AW Schwierigkeiten bei der Immatrikulation", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Besteht eine Möglichkeit mich trotzdem zu immatrikulieren, wenn ich eine Bestehensbestätigung meines Bachelors mit transcript of records vorlege und ich die beglaubigten Zeugnisse nachreiche?", "answer": "Sie finden alle relevanten Informationen zur Immatrikulation, inkl. Zulassungsangebot, Bewerbungsdokumente, Studienplatzannahme, Semesterbeitrag hier: [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW Rechtzeitige Immatrikulation Master MT", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Is it possible to enroll me with a certified certificate of completion and a certified transcript of records since I cannot choose any courses without my immatriculation?", "answer": "To resolve your issue, please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching. They are responsible for all questions regarding matriculation.", "topic": "AW Immatrikulation MiM", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "How can I have the health insurance in Germany and AOK send my information to TUM?", "answer": "For information on health insurance, please check the provided website [REDACTED] and for further questions on the enrollment process and necessary documents, please refer to the TUM Center for Study and Teaching or [REDACTED].", "topic": "AW Cant make the enrollment", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Müssen die BWL ECTs allesamt aus Bachelorfächern gesammelt werden, oder dürfen diese auch aus Masterstudiengängen stammen?", "answer": "Bitte wenden Sie sich an das zuständige Admission Office für den Master in [REDACTED]: [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW AW", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Will the documents listed (application for enrollment with original signature, transcript of records, and an official document from faculty stating graduation instead of a diploma) be sufficient for completing the enrollment at TUM?", "answer": "Please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching: [REDACTED]. Our colleagues are responsible for answering questions regarding accepting your admission offer and enrollment.", "topic": "AW Some Questions About Enrollment", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Kann ich dennoch parallel die Kurse und Prüfungen dieses Semester anfangen? Gibt es eine Übersicht zu den zu belegenden Studienfächern? Muss ich mich dann für das SS24 für den Master noch extra bewerben?", "answer": "Unsere Kolleg*innen unseres Admission Office sind für die Beantwortung von Fragen von Bewerber*innen und Studieninteressierten verantwortlich. Bitte kontaktieren Sie meine Kolleg*innen über: [REDACTED]. Falls verfügbar, geben Sie bitte Ihre Bewerber- oder Immatrikulationsnummer in Ihren E-Mails an.", "topic": "AW Zweiter Master MiM neben Bauing Master TUM", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Können Sie mir sagen, ob das Urlaubssemester bereits genehmigt wurde?", "answer": "Bitte wenden Sie sich mit Ihrer Anfrage an das TUM Center for Study and Teaching. Geben Sie dabei bitte immer Ihre Bewerber- oder Matrikelnummer an. Auf Grund der hohen Nachfrage kann es einige Tage dauern, bis eine Antwort erfolgt.", "topic": "AW Urlaubssemester während Auslandssemester", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Can you please clarify if TUM School of Management has specific partnerships with a business university outside of the EU, or if there is a preferred university that TUM SoM students choose for exchanges or internships, specifically in the US? Also, would I receive funding from TUM, the host university, or any other institution for an exchange program outside the EU?", "answer": "I have forwarded your email to my colleagues from the International Office. They are responsible for questions on our exchange programs and will reply to your email shortly.", "topic": "AW Exchange Student outside of EU", "program": "General Master in Munich"}, {"question": "Can the credits offered in the classes I am taking from the Academy of Innovators at UnternehmerTUM count towards my MMT program?", "answer": "In order to make a binding statement, we need to check the form and content of the completed courses. This can only be done once the course has been completed and a certificate of completion is available. No preliminary review is carried out.", "topic": "AW  Question about classes with credits MMT", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Can I take part in exams during my leave of absence in order to write my thesis next semester?", "answer": "It is not possible to take part in exams during your leave of absence. You are only allowed to take part in retake exams this semester.", "topic": "AW  Register exam during leave of absence", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Ist ein Wechsel des technischen Schwerpunkts von Informatik zu Industrial Engineering im Studiengang MMT noch möglich?", "answer": "Ein Wechsel ist generell möglich, allerdings nur mit Antrag an den Prüfungsausschuss, in dem Sie schildern warum ein Wechsel für Sie relevant ist, umsetzbar.", "topic": "AW  Rückfragen Wechsel technischer Schwerpunkt MMT", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Kann ich die verbleibenden 9 ECTS, die sich aus einem Kurs im Bereich Innovation and Entrepreneurship mit 6 ECTS und einem weiteren Kurs im gleichen Fachbereich mit 3 ECTS zusammensetzen, anrechnen lassen?", "answer": "Grundsätzlich haben Sie die Möglichkeit die Module (auf Masterniveau), die nicht Teil Ihres Bachelors waren auf Anerkennung prüfen zu lassen. Sollte im MMT ein Modul vorkommen, dass mit dem von Ihnen erbrachten Modul eine vermeintliche Entsprechung aufweist, gibt es die Möglichkeit der 1:1 Anerkennung. Melden Sie sich direkt bei den Lehrstühlen mit dem zugehörigen Formular. Sollte es keine Entsprechung im Studiengang geben, bitten wir Sie neben dem Leistungsnachweis auch die Modulbeschreibung zukommen zu lassen.", "topic": "AW  Teilanrechnung Noten Master MMT", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Will the module [REDACTED] (3 credits) be offered this winter semester?", "answer": "It is possible that modules are not offered in some semesters, although the rotation is set to winter semester. This may be due to the availability of the lecturers. To get exact information when the module can be offered again, please contact the chair directly.", "topic": "AW  Inquiry about the module availability", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Ist diese Sorge berechtigt oder gilt der einmalige Wiederholungsversuch der Thesis auch wenn man diese im 6ten Master Semester schreibt?", "answer": "Laut APSO §10 Abs. 6 hätten Sie auch nach dem 6. Fachsemester noch ein Kulanzsemester Zeit Ihr Studium abzuschließen, sofern die vorherigen Credithürden (3.-5. Semester) eingehalten wurden.", "topic": "AW  Master Thesis und Urlaubssemester", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Ist es im Master Management and Technology erlaubt, seine Masterarbeit am Lehrstuhl für Computational Modeling and Simulation von Prof. [REDACTED] zu schreiben?", "answer": "Die Master's Thesis wird über ein Forschungsthema oder Projekt mit wirtschaftswissenschaftlichem Schwerpunkt, häufig an einer Schnittstelle zu den Ingenieur- bzw. Naturwissenschaften, angefertigt. Die Bearbeitung des Themas und Bewertung Ihrer Thesis erfolgt immer in Zusammenarbeit mit einer/m Professor/in bzw. Affiliate Member der TUM School of Management oder einer/m Professor/in anderer Schools, der/die im Studiengang Master Management and Technology lehren, oft auch in Kooperation mit der Industrie oder einem Forschungsinstitut. Ihr/e Prüfer/in kann zeitgleich Ihr/e Betreuer/in für die Abschlussarbeit sein, aber für die Betreuung kommen auch prinzipiell auch andere Personen, wie z.B. wissenschaftliche Mitarbeiter/innen eines Lehrstuhls, infrage.", "topic": "AW  AW  Masterarbeit am Lehrstuhl für Computational Modeling and Simulation", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Kann ich einen Kurs, den ich bereits im Bachelor abgelegt habe, im Rahmen meines Masterstudiums in Management and Technology noch einmal belegen und mir die Klausur anrechnen lassen?", "answer": "Sobald ein Kurs bereits in die Note Ihres Bachelorabschlusses gezählt hat, kann dieser nicht mehr für Ihren Masterabschluss herangezogen werden.", "topic": "AW  Master Management and Technology ", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "What does the warning under my curriculum section regarding the language requirement mean?", "answer": "At the end of the second semester, you must submit a proof of proficiency in German. If you already have a language certificate or another proof of proficiency in German, you can submit it directly to our grade management team.", "topic": "AW  ISSUE  Part of Programme Has Been Definitely Failed", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Is it still possible to choose the course Energy Informatics as an elective, while being in the specialization of Informatics (major)?", "answer": "Your planned approach is therefore possible without any problems.", "topic": "AW  Courses choice", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "Kann ich beide Advanced Seminare im Bereich Innovation & Entrepreneurship belegen und diese jeweils einzeln in meine Management Spezialisierung anrechnen?", "answer": "Ja, Sie können beide Seminare belegen und die Prüfung darin ablegen, da beide in Ihrem Studienbaum modelliert sind und auch keine Hinweise im Modulhandbuch gegen ein solches Vorgehen sprechen. Zudem haben Sie die Zusage der Modulverantwortlichen.", "topic": "AW  Advanced Seminar Belegung", "program": "Master in Management & Technology"}, {"question": "When will you get your visa and be able to come to the country?", "answer": "I will be arriving in Germany by the second week of November (6th November - 10th November).", "topic": "Re Intercultural Training - Nov", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Can I still select the FIM exclusive modules after facing technical issues with the module selection on TUMonline?", "answer": "Yes, you should now be able to see the registration for the three courses in TUMonline.", "topic": "Re issues with FIM module selection", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Can you try submitting the form again and give me feedback if it works now?", "answer": "No explicit answer is provided in the provided text.", "topic": "AW New talent pool @ Allianz Global Investor", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Would you please add me to the Discrete Time Finance exercise?", "answer": "I have just registered you for the exercise.", "topic": "Re Discrete Time Finance Exercise", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Wäre es möglich mich nachträglich einzuschreiben?", "answer": "Ich habe bereits die Information unseres Prüfungsmanagement-Teams erhalten, dass diese den Anmeldezeitraum der genannten Prüfung bis heute verlängert haben. Bitte melden Sie sich daher unbedingt noch heute für die Prüfung selbstständig an...", "topic": "AW Verpasste Prüfungsanmeldung DDIT", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Why did I receive an email saying that I am not registered for the Fit for TUMorrow Day 2023 even though I have already registered?", "answer": "You were not on the Anmeldeliste (registration list), so you were asked to register again and provide your registration confirmation with the details of the workshops and company interviews you desire.", "topic": "RE Invitation Fit for TUMorrow Day 2023", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Kann ich da [REDACTED] ECTS Kurse aus Quant Finance (Investment Risk Management & Trading Seminar) durch E-Lab ersetzen?", "answer": "Wenn Studierende mehr ECTS in einem bestimmten Bereich erbracht haben, als gefordert, werden automatisch die besten Leistungen in den Bereich gezählt. Die Leistungen, die dann nicht in dem Bereich aufgeführt werden, werden als Zusatzleitung auf dem Zeugnis aufgeführt. Somit gibt es also nicht die Möglichkeit, dass du dir die Fächer selber auswählst, die in einem bestimmten Bereich aufgeführt werden.", "topic": "Re Notenaufteilung Max Reinhard", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Can you assist with the error I am facing when registering for the \"[REDACTED]\" Exam?", "answer": "Yes, I have successfully registered for the exam. Thank you so much for your help!", "topic": "Re Error in registration for the exam", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Do I need to take a 6 ETCs module course from an area to meet the requirement or can a 3 ETCs module course suffice?", "answer": "You should select at least one module from 3 out of 4 areas. This is independent of the ECTS.", "topic": "Re Question about requirements regarding electives", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Is there anything possible to do about the fact that I, as a student from the Management and Technology faculty, missed the registration date for the Trading Seminar, but would really love to attend it?", "answer": "Unfortunately, this module is offered exclusively for students of the Master in Finance and Information Management and therefore no others can take this module.", "topic": "AW Trading Seminar (FIM) MA9982 ", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Können wir in diesem Fall auch einfach so hingehen, oder uns irgendwie “nachregistrieren”?", "answer": "leider ist die Anmeldung zu Fit for TUMorrow nicht mehr möglich, da die Vorbereitungen bereits laufen und die Planung auf Grundlage der aktuellen Teilnehmerzahl angestoßen ist.", "topic": "AW Fit for TUMorrow", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Wann wird das Venture Capital Lab angeboten und sind zusätzliche Module mit Beginn des WS [REDACTED] bzw. ab dem SS [REDACTED] in FIM geplant?", "answer": "Das Modul Venture Capital Lab wird im nächsten WS Semester nicht angeboten und es wurden keine Informationen zu den Hintergründen geliefert. Ab dem nächsten Semester wird ein weiteres Modul angeboten: Coding Lab: Deep Reinforcement Learning (FIM) (MGT001400). Das Modul Business Plan: Advanced Seminar wird dieses Wintersemester nicht angeboten und es ist nicht geplant, dieses Modul weiterhin anzubieten.", "topic": "AW Venture Capital Lab (WIB33002) (Sommersemester '24)", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Could you please confirm if a decision has been made on what we are allowed to use for the Basics of FIM exam and provide information on the rules for the 'cheat sheet'?", "answer": "For the Basics of FIM exam (that means for all three parts) the use of one hand written DINA4 page is allowed (you can write on the back and front). You will have to hand in the page with the exam. For the Investment & Financing part an additional formula sheet will be handed out to you together with the exams.", "topic": "AW Basics of FIM Exam Materials Question", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Kann das Modul Advanced Econometrics im WS23/24 auch mit nur 3 Studierenden angeboten werden?", "answer": "Ja, [REDACTED] würde das Modul Advanced Econometrics im WS23/24 sogar nur mit 3 Studierenden anbieten.", "topic": "Aw AW Modul Advanced Econometrics", "program": "Master in Finance & Information Management"}, {"question": "Is there even a point in me sending the official document needed for the credit recognition process this late, and would there be a possibility to speed the assessment up due to the proximity of the exam?", "answer": "After submitting your documents, credit recognition does generally take about 6-8 weeks. Sometimes the process can be faster, but this depends on various factors, such as the number of credit recognitions being processed at that time, the availability of the responsible professor, and if additional documents are required for clarification.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Is there a deadline to apply for credit transfer from my bachelors for one of the mandatory subjects or not? If yes, then what is the deadline?", "answer": "You can apply for the recognition of courses until the end of this semester ([REDACTED]). Please keep the deadline in mind.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can you send me the process on how to transfer credits?", "answer": "You can find the presentation about credit recognition in the Moodle course “Studying @ [REDACTED]”: [REDACTED]. If you click on your intake, you can find the presentation “Credit recognition info session” under “general information.”", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I register for subjects and get my study plan even though I don't have the matriculation certificate yet?", "answer": "Yes, you can only register for courses (and exams) once you are fully enrolled.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I register for courses on TUMonline if I am not fully enrolled yet, and what should I do since my enrollment has not been completed and I cannot register for the courses scheduled for this semester?", "answer": "As long as you are not fully enrolled, you are not able to register for courses on TUMonline. You are welcome to attend the welcome day and lectures starting next week so you don’t miss out on any of the content. You need to make sure that you are fully enrolled before the enrolment deadline.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Ist eine Anmeldung zu den Kursen in TUM Online ausreichend, um an den Lehrveranstaltungen teilnehmen und auf die Lehrinhalte zugreifen zu können?", "answer": "Wenn Sie sich für die Lehrveranstaltungen in TUMOnline anmelden, haben Sie danach automatisch Zugriff auf die entsprechenden Kurse in Moodle. Dort finden Sie für jede Veranstaltung die entsprechenden Inhalte, die für die jeweilige Veranstaltung zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Je nach Lehrstuhl kann sich der Umfang der hochgeladenen Unterlagen unterscheiden.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Will there be an orientation session for MiM students planning to take the thesis next semester, summer term 2024?", "answer": "We will offer an info session concerning the thesis in the new year – during the session, I will explain the process, and we will publish the topics for the summer semester after the session.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "What is the status of the processing of my documents for enrollment, and will the explanation regarding the digital APS certificate be accepted or should I resend all documents by post?", "answer": "Unfortunately, I have no insight into the processing status of your documents at the Center for Study and Teaching. Please get in touch with our colleagues there again to clarify the outstanding points.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "What should I be aware of if I decide to join TUM later?", "answer": "If you decide to join TUM later, it is your responsibility to catch up on the content provided through lectures, seminars, and exercises, as the university will not show consideration for your late arrival. You are also responsible for keeping up with the study progress, which includes achieving a minimum number of credits by the end of specific semesters. Failure to meet these deadlines can lead to deregistration. Additionally, please ensure to follow proper email etiquette when communicating with professors and administration.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Ist es möglich, meine Abschlussdokumente intern weiterzuleiten, sodass der ganze Prozess etwas beschleunigt wird, und ich nicht extra warten muss, um mich für die Kurse einzuschreiben?", "answer": "Die Unterlagen werden vom Zentrum für Studium und Lehre in München (Center for Study and Teaching) bearbeitet. Bitte wenden Sie sich mit Ihrer Frage direkt an unsere Kolleginnen und Kollegen: [REDACTED]", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can you explain the process and implications of postponing my education, and do I have to reapply from zero if I postpone it?", "answer": "You will have to reapply for the corresponding semester via TUMonline. We recommend applying as early as possible to prepare for your trip to Germany. You do not necessarily have to start everything from zero, but you will need to follow the official deferral procedures and deadlines provided on our website.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "How could I proceed with my studies since the insurance company has not sent the required confirmation, and I am unable to register for any courses?", "answer": "The Center for Study and Teaching is responsible for enrolling health insurance in the system, and for immediate assistance, you can call them directly. Once all requirements are met and fully enrolled, you can register for the courses in TUMOnline and will have access to Moodle. If you are already on site, you can ask other students to forward Moodle documents on a transitional basis.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can you provide me with the contact details of companies located in Heilbronn for my Master's Thesis on social Embeddedness between company CEOs and employees?", "answer": "Unfortunately, I do not have any contact data for Heilbronn companies that I could send you.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Can I, as a non-EU student, apply to the Ausländerbehörde to exceed the 120 working days limit by proving the relevance of my job to my studies, and what should I provide from my company to get a confirmation paper from TUM to present to the Ausländerbehörde?", "answer": "Please get in touch with the Ausländerbehörde responsible for you regarding your request. As a rule, you will get information on whether your case officer needs more information from us. Then you can get in touch with us again. Please also contact your health insurance company, as this may affect your student status.", "topic": "Mails PM", "program": "Master in Management in Heilbronn"}, {"question": "Mein Arbeitgeber hat angefragt, bezüglich Marketing am Campus. Ich weiß Sie sind absolut nicht der Ansprechpartner hierfür, aber wissen Sie an wen ich mich dafür wenden kann?", "answer": "Als öffentliche Universität können wir an unserer School nicht ohne Weiteres Marketingaktivitäten am Campus durch Externe unterstützen. Wenn es z.B. um Stellenausschreibungen geht, dann kann sich Ihr Arbeitgeber gerne an die Fachschaft wenden: [REDACTED] Eine weitere Anlaufstelle wäre z.B. auch der Alumni Verein der TUM School of Management (auch für Partnerschaften etc.): [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW  Anfrage Marketing", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Could you please provide me with guidance on how to effectively connect with potential supervisors and ensure a timely response? Additionally, if there are any specific recommendations or suggestions, I would be grateful for your insights.", "answer": "Are you familiar with the guidelines for finding a thesis topic and supervisor? If not, please review the information in our Download Center: [REDACTED] (BMT - Final Thesis – Guidelines). In principle, you can apply to all chairs of the TUM School of Management, Affiliate Members and also to other professors / chairs outside the TUM School of Management who teach at least one module in your study program. You can find contact information, requirements for thesis supervision, and information about topics for each chair at the TUM School of Management by following the provided link. To give you more specific advice, please send me an overview of exactly which topics and in which period you have applied to which chairs / supervisors, and examples of your correspondence. We can then schedule a personal consultation and talk about next steps.", "topic": "AW  Bachelor thesis supervision", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Ist eine Anmeldung zu Klausuren des Wintersemesters möglich, obwohl ich mich momentan nicht anmelden kann, und an wen muss ich mich wenden?", "answer": "Da Sie noch keinen Exmatrikulationsbescheid erhalten haben, können wir Sie aktuell noch (unter Vorbehalt) zu Prüfungen anmelden. Ihre Anfrage habe ich bereits an die zuständigen Kolleg*innen weitergegeben: [REDACTED].", "topic": "AW  Klausureinschreibung", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Wie kann ich mich für die Abschlusszeremonie anmelden und muss ich mich exmatrikulieren; sowie wie wirkt sich dies auf das Abschlusszeugnis aus?", "answer": "Für Informationen zur Graduation Ceremony wenden Sie sich bitte an die zuständigen Kolleg*innen oder besuchen Sie den bereitgestellten Link. Ihr Abschlusszeugnis wird auf das Datum der letzten Prüfungsleistung ausgestellt und die genaue Semesterzahl wird nicht genannt. Sie können einen Antrag auf Exmatrikulation stellen oder werden automatisch zum Ende des Semesters exmatrikuliert, in welchem Ihre Abschlussdokumente ausgestellt werden, vorausgesetzt, Sie haben sich für das entsprechende Semester rückgemeldet. Weitere Informationen zur Exmatrikulation finden Sie unter dem angegebenen Link.", "topic": "AW  Abschlusszeremonie und Extrikulation", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Könnten Sie mir bitte eine entsprechende Bestätigung ausstellen, die bestätigt, ob noch offene Prüfungsleistungen etc. vorhanden sind?", "answer": "Ich habe Ihnen eine entsprechende Bescheinigung ausgestellt.", "topic": "RE  Nachweis ordentlicher Studentenstatus für Werkstudententätigkeit", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Can you send me an informal document from the Examination office/professor confirming that I expect to finish my studies by the end of the summer semester [REDACTED]?", "answer": "I have forwarded your email to my colleagues from the Grade Management Office. They are responsible for these kinds of questions and will take care of your request.", "topic": "RE  document", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "If I successfully accumulate all the required credits, will I be automatically considered as having graduated, or is there an additional application process I need to complete?", "answer": "Students are automatically exmatriculated at the end of the semester in which their graduation documents are issued - provided they have re-registered for that semester. Exmatriculation takes place by law; an application is not necessary in this case. Our Grade Management Team will get in touch with you once you collect the necessary credits to complete your degree, and they will confirm the next steps with you.", "topic": "AW  Inquiry Regarding Graduation Certificate and Procedures", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Wann und auf welchem Wege erfährt man, ob das „checken“ der Dokumente für das Modul \"International Experience\" erfolgreich war?", "answer": "Die Anträge werden laufend bearbeitet, es gibt noch genügend Zeit bis zur Klausur im März, und es ist nicht nötig, bis zum 28.02. zu warten. Es wird darum gebeten, von individuellen Nachfragen zum Bearbeitungsstand abzusehen und etwas Geduld zu haben.", "topic": "AW  Fragen zu International Experience", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Wie kann ich mich nur vom Tum BWL Bachelor abmelden, ohne mich vom Elektrotechnik Master abzumelden?", "answer": "Für die Beantwortung Ihrer Anfrage, wenden Sie sich bitte an das TUM Center for Study and Teaching unter studium@tum.de und geben Sie Ihre Immatrikulationsnummer in Ihrer Nachricht an.", "topic": "AW  Abmeldung vom Studium Tum Bwl", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Können Sie mir bitte eine Liste mit möglichen Projekten für das Projektstudium zukommen lassen, Informationen zum Absolvieren des Projekts im Ausland und in Verbindung mit Film oder Musik geben, und mir die Ablauffristen sowie den idealen Zeitpunkt für das Projektstudium erklären?", "answer": "Grundlegende Informationen zum Projektstudium finden Sie im Merkblatt auf unserer Homepage und im Moodlekurs \"Project Studies Support\". Das Projektstudium ist grundsätzlich im Ausland möglich, muss aber mit Betreuer*innen und Teammitgliedern abgesprochen werden. Eine Kooperation mit einem Unternehmen ist nicht zwingend, es sei denn, Sie möchten eine Vergütung. Es empfiehlt sich, mindestens zwei bis maximal fünf Studierende im Team zu haben und das Projektstudium sollte idealerweise 3 Monate bei Vollzeit und 6 Monate bei Teilzeit dauern. Die Ablauffristen sind nicht festgelegt. Für Angebote können Sie die Webseiten der Lehrstühle konsultieren oder unseren Downloadbereich für Unternehmen nutzen. Eine Liste mit möglichen Projekten oder spezielle Angebote zu Projekten im Ausland wurden nicht direkt bereitgestellt. Bitte lesen Sie die zur Verfügung gestellten Informationen im Detail durch und kontaktieren Sie uns, sollten Sie weitere Fragen haben.", "topic": "AW  Projekt Studium", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Can my fee status be updated because I repaid my fee today and the 17th is the last date of enrollment?", "answer": "We are not the right contact for semester fees. Please get in touch with the TUM Center for Study and Teaching for assistance with enrollment and fee questions.", "topic": "AW  URGENT FEE ISSUE Applicant number  2-[REDACTED] Matriculation number  [REDACTED]", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Could you please provide insights about the necessary procedures involved in changing my specialization and is it a good idea to switch at this point?", "answer": "A later change of specialization might be possible under certain circumstances. To apply, please send a signed application to the Examination Board of the TUM School of Management, in which you give convincing reasons for why you want to change specializations. Please also specify if you would like to request a transfer of credits to another area of your curriculum support in case your application is accepted.", "topic": "AW  Seeking Advice on Specialization Change", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Wann haben Sie Zeit für ein Beratungsgespräch?", "answer": "Eine persönliche Beratung ist nicht nötig, da an der [REDACTED] die Lehrstühle die Module prüfen.", "topic": "AW  Anerkennung von Leistungen", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Would it be possible for me to enrol for the [REDACTED]th semester at TUM SoM even though I have basically finished the programme and am just waiting for the grades and my final Bachelor certificate?", "answer": "Students are automatically exmatriculated at the end of the semester in which their graduation documents are issued, provided they have re-registered for that semester. If you complete all examinations by the end of the current semester and do not re-register for the coming semester, you will be exmatriculated at the end of the current semester. However, if you register for the next semester and your documents are not issued until then, you will be exmatriculated at the end of that semester. Furthermore, you can always be exmatriculated on the exact day using the appropriate form in your TUMonline account.", "topic": "RE  Question regarding my Bachelor", "program": "Bachelor in Management & Technology in Munich"}, {"question": "Sollte man sich für mehrere Fächer anmelden (also mehr als die 12 ECTS, die man dazu wählen kann), damit man sicher die 30 ECTS im ersten Semester belegt? Kann man auch Fächer aus unterschiedlichen Schwerpunkten wählen? Also aus Management & Marketing sowie Economics & Econometrics?", "answer": "Sie können sich für alle Seminare anmelden, die im kommenden Wintersemester angeboten werden. Sobald Sie einen Schwerpunkt in Management ausgewählt haben, können Sie nur noch Module aus diesem gewählten Schwerpunkt wählen. Sie können jedoch innerhalb der Electives in Consumer Science and Technology aus allen anderen Schwerpunkten Modulen wählen und sogar noch weiteren Bereichen, die dort gelistet sind.", "topic": "AW Frage Fächeranmeldung Consumer Science", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Can I take credits and grade for the \"Fundamentals of Strategy\" (WI001128) course and its exercise seminar (WI001128VC) in the upcoming winter semester as part of my Master's in Consumer Science curriculum?", "answer": "The module WI001128 \"Strategies in MNEs\" was offered for the last time in winter semester 2022/23 and is not shown in the curriculum anymore. The alternative module WI001128 “Fundamentals of Strategy” will be offered from winter semester 2023/24 and will be included in the curriculum of the Master of Consumer Science. You will be able to register for the module from the start of winter semester 2023/24.", "topic": "AW Enquiry for information about the course Fundamentals of Strategy (WI001128)", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Could you please provide guidance on the credit transfer process, including any necessary documentation and deadlines?", "answer": "It is possible to transfer completed courses from the MMT study program into the MCS study program, if the courses are included in both curricula. You should compare if the courses you completed within the MMT program are included in your personal Curriculum Support of the MCS program in TUMonline. The credit transfer process details can be found in the document “Recognition of TUM courses, which were attended before starting and during your Master’s at TUM School of Management” on page 2 in the Download-Center of our website under “Master in Consumer Science” --> “Credit Transfer”. However, a transfer of courses is only possible after you are fully matriculated in the MCS program.", "topic": "AW Credit Transfer Assistance Request", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Kann der Kurs \"Energy Markets I\" (WI000946) trotz der freien Anmeldung und der Tatsache, dass er im Curriculum Support nicht aufgeführt wird, als Elective im Master in Consumer Science angerechnet werden?", "answer": "Sie können das Modul \"Energy Markets I\" (WI000946) in die Electives Consumer Science & Technology einbringen. Nach erfolgreichem Bestehen der Prüfung soll sich der Studierende an das Grade Management Team wenden, um das Modul dem Electivebereich zuordnen zu lassen, wobei diese E-Mail als Bestätigung beigelegt werden sollte.", "topic": "AW Frage bzgl", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Wie ist der Fall, wenn ich die Prüfung in dem Modul „Consumer Analytics and Big Data“ nicht bestehe - muss ich die Prüfung dann in der Wiederholungsprüfung nachholen, oder kann ich den Kurs im nächsten Sommersemester wieder belegen und dann das Pflichtmodul abschließen? Wenn ich eine Klausur eines Wahlfaches bestehe, kann ich dann diese Klausur zur Notenverbesserung wiederholen? Denn um an dem Lehrstuhl für Psychologie seine Masterarbeit schreiben zu können, muss man in dem Fach „Introduction to Statistics using R“ eine bestimmte Note erreichen.", "answer": "Es ist nicht möglich, eine Klausur zur Notenverbesserung zu wiederholen. Es obliegt Ihnen, Ihr Studium zu planen – daher auch, in welchem Semester Sie das Pflichtmodul abschließen (solange Sie den Studienfortschritt einhalten).", "topic": "AW Frage zu den Pflichtmodulen  Consumer Science ", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Ich hätte gerne Ihre Beratung bezüglich meines Studienverlaufs, denn durch private Umstände ist mir klar geworden, dass ich mein Studium entweder in Regelstudienzeit mit schlechten Ergebnissen oder mehr als die 4 Semester brauchen werde. Wie kann ich meinen Studienverlauf besser planen, damit ich mein Studium erfolgreich abschließen kann?", "answer": "Solange Sie die in der APSO und FPSO festgelegten Fristen für die Anzahl der zu erbringenden Credits einhalten, können Sie bis zu sechs Fachsemester studieren. APSO sieht vor, dass bis zum Ende des dritten Fachsemesters mindestens 30 Credits, bis zum Ende des vierten Fachsemesters 60 Credits, bis zum Ende des fünften Fachsemesters 90 Credits und bis zum Ende des sechsten Fachsemesters 120 Credits zu erbringen sind. Für individuelle Fragen bezüglich Ihrer Studienplanung können Sie sich gerne innerhalb der Sprechzeiten am Dienstag von 10:00-12:00 Uhr oder Mittwoch von 14:00-16:00 Uhr melden.", "topic": "AW Beratung Studienverlauf Master Consumer Science", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Is it mandatory for students to select one of the available specializations in the Master in Consumer Science at TUM, or is there flexibility in opting out of a specialization altogether, and when is the ideal timing for selecting a specialization?", "answer": "In the Master in Consumer Science you have to choose one of the four options that are listed within the node “Specialization in Management”, and you have to achieve 24 ECTS credits within your chosen option. One of the options is “No management specialization chosen” which means that you can choose from all listed modules below, including Advanced Seminars. There is no set deadline for choosing a specialization, and it is set by clicking on the small box behind it or by registering for the first exam within that specialization. You can start with Advanced Seminars from the second semester on, and there is flexibility to move completed courses later, after you have chosen your Specialization in Management. However, only courses that are listed in your chosen specialization can be moved from the Electives.", "topic": "AW Inquiry Regarding Specializations in the Consumer Science Program", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "If I take the course successfully, it will be listed on a separate sheet in my transcript, but without the credits shown. I will still have to take the exam to make this happen, right? As a Master's student, if I take the Bachelor course with the option of \"free registration,\" am I still allowed to take the exam for this course?", "answer": "You understood correctly. The course will only be shown on a separate sheet on your transcript if you passed the exam of the course. You are allowed to take the exam of the course as a free subject (except if the course has limited capacities, but then you wouldn´t be able to register anymore at this point).", "topic": "AW Questions about switching major at SOM and double-degree ", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "How can I get a confirmation that I'll definitely graduate with at least a 4.0 in my thesis?", "answer": "Officially, 4.0 confirmations are no longer issued in advance by our Grademanagement team. In urgent cases, please contact the examiner or supervisor of your thesis and ask for a confirmation in advance that you passed the thesis. Students can also request preliminary final documents from the central Graduation Office of TUM via the provided website.", "topic": "AW Confirmation for graduation", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Can the course \"[REDACTED]\" that I completed during my Bachelor's degree with a total of 3 ECTS credits be recognized as part of the Electives in my Master's in Consumer Science program at TUM?", "answer": "The module [REDACTED] is held on Bachelor´s level and therefore can´t be recognized towards your study program in your Master's in Consumer Science at TUM.", "topic": "AW Recognition of Credits - Electives", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Ist dies ein Fehler oder warum wurde dies im Nachhinein geändert? Bitte bestätigen Sie mir, dass dieser Kurs tatsächlich nicht mehr als Elective in der Spezialisierung Innovation & Entrepreneurship zu wählen ist, sodass ich mich von dieser Prüfung abmelden kann.", "answer": "Die Lehrveranstaltung „Strategies in MNEs“ ([REDACTED]) wird leider seit Ende des Wintersemesters 2022/23 nicht mehr angeboten. Das Modul ist jedoch weiterhin als inaktives Modul in dem Schwerpunkt „Innovation and Entrepreneurship“ gelistet. [...] Die Prüfung zu dem Modul wird in diesem Sommersemester 2023 noch angeboten und Sie können das Modul weiterhin in Ihren Management-Schwerpunkt einbringen.", "topic": "AW DRINGEND Änderung Studienplankontext von Strategies in MNEs", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "Can accommodations be made to enable participation in some of the Master in Consumer Science courses online due to visa processing issues caused by the outbreak of the war in [REDACTED], and what are the available options if it's not possible?", "answer": "Late arrival during studies is strongly advised against as it is likely to cause problems with study progress monitoring, and taking a leave of absence is not possible in your situation. You may defer your studies by following the information on reserving your spot. If you decide to start your studies in the current semester, you could complete modules from the Electives in Consumer Science and Technology online and select a Specialization in Management later. Online courses such as \"[REDACTED]\" in the \"[REDACTED]\" section can be considered, and other TUM courses at the Master’s level not included in the MCS curriculum may also be recognized towards the Electives if they are held online. You must plan your studies and catch up on lost work on your own if joining later.", "topic": "Re Master in Consumer Science Incoming Student ([REDACTED]) - Delayed Visa", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "An wen kann ich mich bezüglich der Anrechnung meiner bis dato erbrachten Kurse im Bereich \"No Specialization\" wenden?", "answer": "Dafür wenden Sie sich bitte an unser Grade Management Team: [REDACTED]", "topic": "AW Anrechnung Kurse Auslandssemester für M", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}, {"question": "If I gain those 36 credits this semester, will I automatically be de-registered from my study program? Would it be possible, even already having all the credits achieved, to register for another semester to take one more subject to \"cover\" a bad grade received?", "answer": "Students are automatically exmatriculated at the end of the semester in which their graduation documents are issued - provided they have re-registered for that semester. Exmatriculation takes place by law; an application is not necessary for exmatriculation in this case. If you want to stay enrolled for another semester for grade improvement, please inform our Grade Management team about it.", "topic": "AW Study related question", "program": "Master in Consumer Science"}]